<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="4"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[Chapter 01












                           Yamaka Wagga - The Pairs]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[1




                                                          1
                 Manopubbaṅgamā dhammā ,
                 manoseṭṭhā manomayā,

                 manasā ce paduṭṭhena              2

                 bhāsati vā karoti vā,
                 tato naṁ dukkham-anveti

                 cakkaṁ va vahato padaṁ


                 All mental phenomena have mind as their forerunner; they

                 have mind as their chief; they are mind-made. If one speaks
                 or acts with an evil mind, 'dukkha'                  3  follows him just as the

                 wheel follows the hoofprint of the ox that draws the cart.





                 1. manopubbangama dhamma: All mental phenomena have Mind
                 as their forerunner in the sense that Mind is the most dominant,

                 and it is the cause of the other three mental phenomena, namely,
                 Feeling (vedana), Perception (sanna) and Mental Formations or

                 Mental Concomitants (sankhara). These three have Mind or
                 Consciousness (vinnana) as their forerunner, because although

                 they arise simultaneously with Mind they cannot arise if Mind does
                 not arise.


                 2. manasa ce padutthena (Verse 1): Manasa here means intention

                 or volition (cetana); volition leads one to the performance of
                 volitional actions, both good and evil. This volition and the

                 resultant actions constitute kamma; and kamma always follows
                 one to produce results. Cakkhupala's blindness (Verse 1)














                                                                                                        2]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[3. dukkha: In this context, dukkha mens suffering, or physical

                 or     mental        pain,       misfortune,         unsatisfactoriness,            evil
                 consequences, etc., and rebirth in the lower planes of

                 existence or in the lower strata of human society if born in the

                 human world.
































                 Cakkhupalatthera Vatthu - The Story of Thera

                 Cakkhupala


                 the Buddha While residing at the Jetavana monastery in

                 Savatthi, the Buddha uttered Verse (1) of this book, with

                 reference to Cakkhupala, a blind thera.


                 On one occasion, Thera Cakkhupala came to pay homage to
                 the Buddha at the Jetavana monastery. One night, while

                 pacing up and down in meditation, the thera accidentally

                 stepped on some insects. In the morning, some bhikkhus
                 visiting the thera found the dead insects. They thought ill of

                 the thera and reported the matter to the Buddha. The Buddha

                 asked them whether they had seen the thera killing the
                 insects. When they answered in the negative, said, "Just as






                                                                                                        3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[you had not seen him killing, so also he had not seen those

                 living insects. Besides, as the thera had already attained
                 arahatship he could have no intention of killing and so was

                 quite innocent." On being asked why Cakkhupala was blind

                 although he was an arahat, the Buddha told the following
                 story:


                 Cakkhupala was a physician in one of his past existences.

                 Once, he had deliberately made a woman patient blind. That

                 woman had promised him to become his slave, together with
                 her children, if her eyes were completely cured. Fearing that

                 she and her children would have to become slaves, she lied

                 to the physician. She told him that her eyes were getting
                 worse when, in fact, they were perfectly cured. The physician

                 knew she was deceiving him, so in revenge, he gave her

                 another ointment, which made her totally blind. As a result of
                 this evil deed the physician lost his eyesight many times in his

                 later existences.


                 Then the Buddha spoke in verse as follows:



                  Verse 1: All mental phenomena have mind as their
                  forerunner; they have mind as their chief; they are

                  mind-made. If one speaks or acts with an evil mind,

                  'dukkha' follows him just as the wheel follows the hoofprint
                  of the ox that draws the cart.





                 At the end of the discourse, thirty thousand bhikkhus attained
                 arahantship.














                                                                                                        4]]></page></pages></Search>